Register of the United States Army European Command, Historical Division Typescript Studies, 1945-1954
Hoover Institution Archives
United States Army European Command, Historical Division Typescript Studies,
1945-1954
66026
United States. Army. European Command. Historical Division
60 manuscript boxes (25.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Relates to German military operations in Europe, on the Eastern Front, and in the Mediterranean Theater, during World War II. Studies prepared by former high-ranking German Army officers for the Foreign Military Studies Program of the Historical Division, U.S. Army, Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Note
Carbon copies. Originals in: U.S. National Archives, College Park, Maryland.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1966.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The description of the reports in this collection are drawn from the Guide to Foreign Military Studies, 1945-54; Catalog & Index (Headquarters, United States Army, Europe, 1954). Microfiche Publication M1035.
The Hoover Institution Archives does not have all the documents listed in this guide. Consult the following collection content list to find out which documents are present in the Hoover Institution Archives.
Many of the studies have been published in World War II German Military Studies, 24 vols. Donald S. Detweiler, ed. (New York: Garland Publishing, 1979)
Preface, Guide to Foreign Military Studies, 1945-54; Catalog & Index (Headquarters, United States Army, Europe, 1954).
This catalog and index is a guide to the manuscripts produced under the Foreign Military Studies Program of the Historical Division, United States Army, Europe, and of predecessor commands since 1945. Most of these manuscripts were prepared by former high-ranking officers of the German Armed Forces, writing under the sponsorship of their former adversaries. The program therefore represents an unusual degree of collaboration between officers of nations recently at war.
The Foreign Military Studies Program actually began shortly after V-E Day, when Allied interrogators first questioned certain prominent German prisoners of war. Results were so encouraging that the program was expanded; written questions replaced oral interrogation, and later certain highly-placed German officers were asked to prepare a series of monographs.
Originally the mission of the program was only to obtain information on enemy operations in the European Theater for use in the preparation of an official history of the U.S. Army in World War II. In 1946 the program was broadened to include the Mediterranean and Russian war theaters. Beginning in 1947 emphasis was placed on the preparation of operational studies for use by U.S. Army planning and training agencies and service schools. The result has been the collection of a large amount of useful information about the German Armed Forces, prepared by German military experts. While the primary aim of the program has remained unchanged, many of the more recent studies have analyzed the German experience with a view toward deriving useful lessons.
The authors were usually key participants in the events which they described and were able to supply information not otherwise available. In many cases they have supplemented or refreshed their memories by consulting with their military associates. It must be remembered, however, that some contributors are professional military leaders, not historians or writers. While for the most part they have tried to be thorough and objective, they view events primarily in terms of their own experience.
In the initial phases of the program all of the contributors were prisoners of war or internees; participation, however, was always voluntary. While participants were reimbursed for their work, they have been motivated mainly by professional interest and by the desire to promote western solidarity and mutual defense.
In 1945, after most of the contributors had returned to civilian life, the administrative structure and tempo of the program was changed. Contributors now prepare studies in their own homes under the supervision of a small control group, composed of selected high-ranking German officers.
Many of the early manuscripts were inadequately translated and were assigned inappropriate titles. Some of these manuscripts have been reissued in revised versions but in most cases the original titles have been retained to facilitate identification.
During the early years of the program, contributors had to rely largely on their memories, since the basic documents had been destroyed or were otherwise unavailable to them. Within the past few months basic documents have been increasingly provided to contributors, who now place more emphasis on careful documentation. Current studies are now checked against known sources and in some cases are considerably revised in the English version. Although individual studies will continue to vary in quality, the collection as a whole constitutes a noteworthy contribution to the history of World War II.
As the number of manuscripts increased, it became essential to index the collection in order to make its contents more readily available. This project was begun in September 1951 by General der Artillerie Friedrich von Boetticher, German military attaché to the United States from 1933 to 1941. Initially the index was planned to include only those manuscripts which had been translated and were considered to contain useful military lessons. This phase of the project was virtually completed by spring 1952, when General von Boetticher was compelled for personal reasons to give up the work. At that time it was decided to index and evaluate all of the manuscripts in the collection, regardless of their nature. This task was undertaken by General der Artillerie Anton Freiherr von Bechtolsheim, who completed the indexing and evaluated each study with regard to its historical, operational, and technical interest.
The present guide contains a catalog of manuscripts and three indexes--by topic, by military unit, and by author. Most entries in the catalog include a short statement describing the contents and usefulness of the study.
Certain translation difficulties are reflected in this guide. Germany military terms do not always have exact American equivalents and cannot be expressed briefly in precise military language. Untranslated terms appearing in this guide are explained in the glossary, page 252. This difficulty in arriving at standardized and generally accepted translations of German military terms has been a persistent problem in preparing the manuscripts; the researcher may even feel the need for an expansion and revision of U.S. military terminology.
Studies now in preparation and those projected will also be indexed and catalogued. Errata and addenda sheets will be issued from time to time, but a complete revision of the catalog does not seem practicable in the near future. A limited number of copies of this guide are available to official agencies, particularly to those which possess a substantial number of the studies.
W.S. Nye, Colonel, Artillery, Karlsruhe Chief Historian, June 1954 Hq. U.S. Army, Europe
Access Points
Germany. Heer; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Eastern; World War, 1939-1945--Germany; Germany
Collection Contents
- A-Series manuscripts. (Box 1-5)
  When the first complete inventory of studies was made in mid-1946, all translated manuscripts on hand were designated the A-series. Numbers were assigned in reverse order, from A-1000 to A-855, and the series was then closed. All authors in this series were in prisoner of war status. During the summer of 1945 procedure followed a technique originating with intelligence agencies: each manuscript consisted of a transcribed oral interview which was afterward submitted to the person interviewed for checking and signature. This procedure was soon discarded in favor of written answers to written questionnaires. While some of the questionnaires are missing, the writer's statements are nevertheless clear. A very few studies, dated 1947, are revisions of earlier manuscripts. In some cases the date of writing is unknown. All A-series manuscript titles are drawn from the Guide to Foreign Military Studies, 1945-54; Catalog & Index (Headquarters, United States Army, Europe, 1954)
  - A-855 History of the Attempt on Hitler's Life (20 Jul. 1944). By Generalmajor Rudolf Freiherr von Gersdorff; 15 pp; 1946. Personal experiences of one of the conspirators. (Box 1)
  - A-856 Attack on Alençon. By General der Panzertruppen Heinrich von Luettwitz; 4 pp; 1946. Operations of the 2d Panzer Division in Normandy and northern France, 1944. (English text not available in USAREUR.) (Box 1)
  - A-858 The Course of Events of the German Offensive in the Ardennes (16 Dec. 1944-14 Jan. 1945). By Major Percy E. Schramm; 43 pp; 1945. The author kept the war diary of the Wehrmacht Operations Staff. (German text not available in USAREUR.) (Box 1)
  - A-860 Notes on the Execution of War Diaries in the German Armed Forces. By Major Percy E. Schramm; 11 pp; 1945. The author kept the war diary of the Wehrmacht Operations Staff. (Box 1)
  - A-861 Answers to the Questions of 15 Feb. 1946. By Major Percy E. Schramm; 2 pp; 1946. Command organization for the Ardennes offensive, 1944. (Box 1)
  - A-863 Fifth Panzer Army (November 1944). By Generalmajor Carl Wagener; 5 pp; 1945. Defense against the American attack on the Roer, 1944. (Box 1)
  - A-864 Pas de Calais Naval Forces--Normandy. By Vizeadmiral Friedrich Frisius; 6 pp; 1946. Preparations for coastal defense in a section north of the Seine. (Box 1)
  - A-867 Answer to Questions on Source-Documents for Military History. By Major Herbert Buechs; 2 pp; 1945. By the aid to General Jodl. (Box 1)
  - A-868 German Reaction to the Invasion of Southern France. By Generaloberst Johannes Blaskowitz; 3 pp; 1945. (Box 1)
  - A-869 Strength and Location of the German Air Force in South France. By Major Herbert Buechs; 3 pp. (Box 1)
  - A-870 Beck Against Hitler. By Generalleutnant Dr. Hans Speidel; 12 pp; 1947. A sworn statement regarding the Army High Command's attitude towards Adolf Hitler. (Box 1)
  - A-871 21st Panzer Division in Combat Against American Troops in France and Germany. By Generalleutnant Edgar Feuchtinger; 62 pp. (Box 1)
  - A-872 Strength, Organization, Armament, and Equipment of Troops in Battle. By General der Panzertruppen Hasso von Manteuffel; 51 pp; OCMH multilith; 1946. (Box 1)
  - A-873 Commitment of the 116th Panzer Division in the Ardennes (16-26 Dec. 1944). By Generalmajor Siegfried von Waldenburg; 28 pp, 6 illus; 1945. (Box 1)
  - A-874 Commitment of the 116th Panzer Division in the Ardennes, 1944-45. By Generalmajor Siegfried von Waldenburg; 17 pp; 1946. (Box 1)
  - A-875 Southern France (15 Aug.-15 Sep. 1944). By Generalleutnant W. Richter; 5 pp. (Box 1)
  - A-876 Ardennes Offensive of Seventh Army (16 Dec. 1944-25 Jan. 1945). By General der Panzertruppen Erich Brandenberger; 155 pp, 6 illus; 1946. Plans, preparations, and a detailed account of the operations, including the immediate aftermath, described by the acting army commander. (Box 1)
  - A-877 Commitment of the I SS Panzer Corps During the Ardennes Offensive (16 Dec. 1944-25 Jan. 1945). By General der Waffen SS H. Priess; 59 pp; 1946. (Box 1)
  - A-878 189th Reserve Division (15 Aug.-14 Sep. 1944). By Generalleutnant Richard von Schwerin; 8 pp; 1946. (Box 1)
  - A-879 The Battle at Vellersexel Against the 45th American Infantry Division (7-11 Sep. 1944). By Generalmajor J. Degener; 18pp; 1946. By the commander of the participating German forces. (Box 1)
  - A-880 The 11th Panzer Division in Southern France (15 Aug.-14 Sep. 1944). By Generalleutnant W. von Wietersheim; 20 pp; 1946. Withdrawal from Southern France. (Box 1)
  - A-882 Battles in Southern France. By Oberst Horst Wilutzky; 35 pp. Army (Box 1)
  - A-883 Group G in southern France up to mid-September 1944. (Two manuscripts bound together.) (Box 1)
  - A-885 The LXIV Corps from August to November 1944. By Major i.G. Kurt Schuster; 19 pp; 1946. From the Loire to the Moselle. (Box 2)
  - A-886 The Retreat from Southwestern France (19 Aug.-15 Sep. 1944). By Generalmajor Hans Taeglichsbeck; 7 pp; 1946. Withdrawal from Niort to Dijon, Sep. 1944. (Box 2)
  - A-887 Report on the Measures Prepared for the Defense of Bordeaux (1943- 44). By Generalmajor Gustav Seiz; 4 pp; 1946. (Box 2)
  - A-888 Southern France. By General der Infanterie Baptist Kniess; 9 pp; 1946. Strategy of operations. (Box 2)
  - A-890 Southern France (Jul. 1943-Mar. 1944). By General der Infanterie Erich Petersen; 12 pp; 1946. IV Luftwaffe Field Corps. (Box 2)
  - A-891 The Battle of the Huertgen Forest (Nov.-Early Dec. 1944). By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 28 pp; 1945. From the viewpoint of the German Seventh Army. (Box 2)
  - A-894 Normandy, COBRA and Mortain. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 14 pp; 1945. By the Seventh Army chief of staff. (Box 2)
  - A-895 Critique of the Defense Against Invasion. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 11 pp; 1945. Comments on the defense against amphibious landings in France, by the Seventh Army chief of staff. (Box 2)
  - A-896 Answers to Questions Asked General Westphal. By General der Kavallerie Siegfried Westphal; 11 pp; 1945. Problems in defense of the West, 1944. (Box 2)
  - A-897 Ludendorff Bridge at Remagen. By Generalfeldmarschall Albert Kesselring; 3 pp; 1945. (Box 2)
  - A-898 Action of the 6th Parachute Division in Northern France (1944). By Generalleutnant R. von Heyking; 18 pp; 1946. By the division commander. (Box 2)
  - A-899 Fifth Panzer Army Rear Area (24 Aug.-10 Sep. 1944). By Generalmajor Walter Leuze; 9 pp; 1946. (Box 2)
  - A-900 Seventh and First Army Rear Areas (Aug.-Sep. 1944). By Generalmajor Curt Souchay; 5 pp; 1946. (Box 2)
  - A-901 The Withdrawal from France. By Generalleutnant Fritz Bayerlein; 5 pp; 1946. The Panzer Lehr Division. (Box 2)
  - A-902 Panzer Lehr Division (24-25 Jul. 1944). By Generalleutnant F. Bayerlein; 4 pp; 1945. Effect of Allied air attack on the Panzer Lehr Division. (Box 2)
  - A-903 Panzer Lehr Division (15-20 Jul. 1944). By Generalleutnant F. Bayerlein; 16 pp. Operations in Normandy. (Box 2)
  - A-904 Avranches. By General der Panzertruppen Heinrich Freiherr von Luettwitz; 21 pp; 1945. Operations of the 2d Panzer Division in Normandy, 1944, described by the division commander. (English text not available in USAREUR.) (Box 2)
  - A-905 116th Panzer Division (1-9 Nov. 1944). By Generalmajor S. von Waldenburg; 3 pp. (Box 2)
  - A-906 Answers to Major Hechler's Questionnaire. By Generalleutnant Schimpf; 3 pp; 1945. Operations of the 3d Parachute Division in Normandy, 26 July-5 August 1944, described by the division commander. (Box 2)
  - A-907 Seventh Army (20 Jun.-20 Aug. 1944). By Generaloberst (Waffen SS) Paul Hausser; 9 pp; 1945. By the army commander. (Box 2)
  - A-909 The Ardennes Offensive. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 22 pp. Seventh Army in the Battle of the Bulge, described by the army chief of staff. (Box 2)
  - A-910 Bombing and Operation COBRA. By Sanitaets-Unteroffizier Walter Klein; 9 pp; 1945. A medical corpsman's recollections of Operation COBRA in Normandy, 24-30 Jul. 1944. A picture of general conditions on the German side. (Box 2)
  - A-911 First Army Headquarters (20 Jun.-10 Aug. 1944). By Oberst i.G. Albert Emmerich; 5 pp. (Box 2)
  - A-912 German Attitudes Toward the U.S. (1939-43). By Generalfeldmarschall Wilhelm Keitel; 3 pp; 1945. Questions on the high level strategy of World War II. (Box 2)
  - A-913 Invasion and Normandy Campaign. By Generaloberst Alfred Jodl; 5 pp; 1945. (Box 2)
  - A-914 Answers to Questions Put to General Jodl. By Generaloberst Alfred Jodl; 8 pp; 1945. Strategy prior to 1944. (Box 2)
  - A-915 Answers to Questions on Normandy. By Generalfeldmarschall Wilhelm Keitel and Generaloberst Alfred Jodl; 6 pp; 1945. (Box 2)
  - A-916 Answers to Questions Directed to General Blaskowitz. By Generaloberst Johannes Blaskowitz; 2 pp; 1945. Operations in Lorraine, Sep. 1944. (Box 2)
  - A-917 The Truth About "Katyn." By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 7 pp; 1946. By the general staff officer charged with the direction of interrogation and exhumation. (Box 2)
  - A-918 Comments on Seventh Army War Diary. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 7 pp; 1945. Comments by the army chief of staff on Volume 5 of the Seventh Army war diary (Avranches, Aug. 1944). (Box 2)
  - A-920 From Counterattack at Avranches to the Falaise Pocket. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 15 pp; 1945. By the Seventh Army chief of staff. (Box 2)
  - A-921 Avranches Counterattack, Seventh Army (29 Jul.-14 Aug. 1944). By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 48 pp; 1945. By the army chief of staff. (Box 2)
  - A-922 Panzer Group Eberbach and the Falaise Encirclement. By General der Panzertruppen Hans Eberbach; 32 pp, 3 illus; 1946. The period 1 Jul.-20 Aug. 1944, with reasons for the German defeat. (Box 3)
  - A-923 Northern France (25 Jul.-14 Sep. 1944). By General der Fallschirmtruppen Eugen Meindl; 48 pp; 1946. Operations of II Parachute Corps in Normandy and northern France, described by the corps commander. (Box 3)
  - A-924 Operations of Sixth Panzer Army (1944-45). By SS Generalmajor Fritz Kraemer; 60 pp; 1945. Action in the Ardennes, described by the army chief of staff. (Box 3)
  - A-925 Report on Activity of Colonel (GSC) Reichhelm. By Oberst i.G. Guenther Reichhelm; 49 pp; 1945. Army Group B on the Western Front from October 1944 to spring 1945. Written from memory by the army group operations officer. (Box 3)
  - A-926 I SS Panzer Corps--Ardennes--Special Questions. By Oberst R. Lehmann; 4 pp; 1946. (Box 3)
  - A-927 The Operations after the Breakthrough at Avranches. By Generaloberst Alfred Jodl; 10 pp; 1945. The fighting on Germany's western frontier, autumn 1944. (Box 3)
  - A-928 Questionnaire on the Ardennes Offensive. By Generalfeldmarschall W. Keitel and Generaloberst A. Jodl; 7 pp; 1945. Answered in July 1945. (Box 3)
  - A-929 Ardennes Campaign. By General der Artillerie W. Lucht; 2 pp. The 18th Infantry Division in the Ardennes offensive. (Box 3)
  - A-930 212th Volks Grenadier Division--Ardennes (16 Dec. 1944-25 Jan. 1945). By Generalleutnant Franz Sensfuss; 7 pp; 1946. (Box 3)
  - A-931 212th Volks Grenadier Division--Ardennes. By Generalleutnant Franz Sensfuss; 9 pp; 1946. (Box 3)
  - A-932 Evaluation and Equipment of the Units Attached to Seventh Army during the Ardennes Offensive. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 5 pp. (Box 3)
  - A-933 Results of the Ardennes Offensive. By Generalmajor R. von Gersdorff; 8 pp; 1946. By the Seventh Army chief of staff. (Box 3)
  - A-934 Seventh Army (16 Dec. 1944-16 Jan. 1945); Nineteenth Army (28 Mar.-5 May 1945). By General der Panzertruppen Erich Brandenberger; 17 pp. Seventh Army in the Ardennes; Nineteenth Army in Apr. 1945. (Box 3)
  - A-935 Answers to Questions (Ardennes Offensive). By General der Infanterie Otto Hitzfeld; 2 pp; 1945. Operations of LXVII Corps. (Box 3)
  - A-936 Ardennes Offensive. By General der Infanterie Otto Hitzfeld; 22 pp; 1945. LXVII Corps, 16-25 Dec. 1944. (Box 3)
  - A-937 The Ardennes Offensive (December 1944). By General der Infanterie Otto Hitzfeld; 20 pp; 1946. Operations of LXVII Corps, described by its commander. (Box 3)
  - A-938 XLVII Panzer Corps--Ardennes. By General der Panzertruppen Heinrich von Luettwitz; 5 pp; 1945. Operations of XLVII Panzer Corps, Dec. 1944, described by its commander. (Box 3)
  - A-939 The Assignment of the XLVII Panzer Corps in the Ardennes, 1944-45. By General der Panzertruppen Heinrich von Luettwitz; 24 pp. (Box 3)
  - A-940 XLVII Panzer Corps in the Ardennes Offensive. By General der Panzertruppen Heinrich von Luettwitz; 18 pp; 1946. (Box 3)
  - A-941 Panzer Lehr Division (1 Dec. 1944-26 Jan. 1945). By Generalleutnant F. Bayerlein; 8 pp; 1945. Role in the Ardennes offensive, described by the division commander. (Box 3)
  - A-943 Additional Questions--Ardennes Offensive. By Generalleutnant F. Bayerlein; 5 pp; 1946. Comments on British and American countermeasures. (Box 3)
  - A-945 Additional Questions--Ardennes Offensive. By Generalleutnant F. Bayerlein; 3 pp; 1946. Additional remarks on operations from 11-20 Jan. 1945 (Houffalize area.) (Box 3)
  - A-946 Southern France. By Generalleutnant Karl Pflaum; 7 pp; 1946. The 157th Reserve Division, 15 Aug.-1 Sep. 1944. (Box 3)
  - A-947 The American Campaign on the Western Front. By Generalleutnant Otto Kohl; 2 pp. Liaison Staff Lyons, Aug.-Sep. 1944. (Box 3)
  - A-948 Organization Controlled by Military Commander, France. By Oberst Wilhelm Arendts; 5 pp; 1946. Military government in the area of Army Group G, southern France. (Box 3)
  - A-949 War History Reports--Activity of the Staff of Army Group G (1 May- 26 Aug. 1944). By General der Artillerie Edgar Theisen; 7 pp; 1946. (Box 3)
  - A-950 Nineteenth Army--Supply and Administration. By Generalintendant Otto Witek; 14 pp. An army supply officer in southern France, 1944. (Box 3)
  - A-951 Report on Withdrawal of 732d Liaison Staff (30 Aug.-6 Sep. 1944) By Generalmajor Johannes Hahn; 3 pp; 1946. (Box 4)
  - A-952 In Vichy After the American Landing. By Generalleutnant Alexander Freiherr von Neubronn; 4 pp; 1946. The author was German Liaison Officer in Vichy. (Box 4)
  - A-953 933d Infantry Regiment--Southern France to the Vosges (Aug.-Sep. 1944). By Oberst Walther Rolin; 7 pp; 1946. (Box 4)
  - A-954 Report on Events in Southern France and the Rhineland. By Generalmajor Felix Meissner; 11 pp; 1946. Army Group G signal communications in southern France and the Rhineland. (Box 4)
  - A-955 Report on the Campaign in Northern France, the Rhineland, and the Ardennes. By Oberst i.G. Hans-Huergen Dingler; 11 pp; 1946. LVIII Panzer Corps from Normandy to the Ruhr pocket; described by the corps chief of staff. (Box 4)
  - A-956 6th Parachute Division--Combat in Northern France (to 24 Aug. 1944). By Generalleutnant Ruediger von Heyking; 24 pp; 1946. (Box 4)
  - A-957 Boulogne (15 Aug.-22 Sep. 1944). By Generalleutnant Ferdinand Heim; 9 pp; 1946. (Box 4)
  - A-958 Military Commander, Belgium and Northern France--1944. By Generalmajor Wilhelm Heider; 1 p; 1946. (Box 4)
  - A-959 16th Luftwaffe Field Division in Normandy (1-23 Jul. 1944). By Generalleutnant Karl Sievers; 3 pp; 1946. (Box 4)
  - A-960 Report Concerning the Retreat of the 159th Division. By Generalmajor Gustav Seiz; 5 pp; 1946. Withdrawal from southern France. (Box 4)
  - A-961 Fifth Panzer Army--Ardennes (Special Questions). By Generalmajor Carl Wagener; 8 pp; 1945. (Box 4)
  - A-962 Fifth Panzer Army--Ardennes (General Comments). By Generalmajor Carl Wagener; 5 pp; 1945. (Box 4)
  - A-963 Main Reasons for the Failure of the Ardennes Offensive. By Generalmajor Carl Wagener; 17 pp; 1945. (Box 4)
  - A-964 Army Group B (25 Jan.-21 Mar. 1945) Report of the Chief of Staff. (Box 4)